{"tossups": [{}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man linked emotions, chance, and politics in a \u201cremarkable trinity\u201d of motives. This</b> <b>man claimed that an attacking army could operate until it reached the (+)</b> <b>culminating</b> <b>point, when it would give up and leave the defending army to triumph. This man noted that three quarters of combat operations were conducted under uncertain conditions. The experience of serving in the losing army at the Battle of (*)</b> Jena-Auerstedt influenced, for the points, what Prussian military theorist who coined the term \u201cfog of war\u201d and wrote<em> On War</em>?", "answer": "Carl von<b> Clausewitz</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man traveled with Levi Pettibone on a three month journey through the Ozarks. This man negotiated the acquisition of over a third of the territory of present-day Michigan via an 1836 Treaty of Washington. As a geologist on the Lewis Cass Expedition, this man (+) coined the name of the headwaters of the Mississippi, Lake Itasca. This man\u2019s marriage to a half-Ojibwe woman contributed to his understanding of Native American traditions that inspired (*) </b> Henry Wadsworth Longfellow\u2019s poem<em> Hiawatha</em>. For the points, name this surveyor who wrote<em> Indian Tribes of the United States</em>.", "answer": "Henry Rowe<b> Schoolcraft</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>In this city, the White Two-Headed Eagle acted as a nationalist front. Members of the Union of the Archangel Michael who were associated with the Black Hundreds shut down this city\u2019s local Prosvita society. (+) Bogdanovka was a concentration camp created during a massacre in this city carried out by the Romanian government in 1941. A scene with a baby (*) </b> stroller rolling down a set of steps of this city can be found in the film<em> Battleship Potemkin</em>, which depicts a 1905 pogrom in, for the points, what Black Sea port city in modern-day Ukraine?", "answer": "<b> Odessa</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>A ruler of these people named Laoshang made a cup out of a Yuezhi king\u2019s skull while conquering Gansu. Dou Xian ended the northern kingdom of these people at the Battle of</b> <b>the Altai Mountains. These people, who ruled the Xia state during the (+)</b> <b>16 Kingdoms</b> <b>period, began warring with the Han Dynasty after Emperor Wu failed to trap them at the Battle of Mayi. After these people won the (*)</b> Battle of Baideng Emperor Gaozu of Han initiated the heqin system of diplomatic marriage. For the points, name these nomadic people, primarily from Mongolia, whose empire was founded by Modu Chanyu.", "answer": "<b> Xiongnu</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>One of these pieces by Philip Glass uses a flute to depict the title Native American girl in its middle \u201cSacajawea\u201d movement and is subtitled \u201cAfter Lewis and Clark.\u201d The final seventeen measures of the third piece in this genre by Bela Bartok were orchestrated by his student Tibor Serly. The</b><em><b> Allegro ma non tanto</b></em><b> first movement of Sergei Rachmaninoff\u2019s (+) third piece of this type features two alternate cadenza. Paul Wittgenstein, who lost his right arm in World War I, commissioned a one-movement example of this piece (*)</b> \u201cfor the left hand\u201d from Maurice Ravel. For the points, name this type of musical composition that features the orchestra supporting a keyboard soloist.", "answer": "<b> piano concerto</b> (prompt on concerto)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>William Baffin died on an expedition this ruler ordered, which led to a threat by the Duke of Buckingham to sue the English East India Company. This ruler built a new capital and resettled Armenian people there to stimulate the silk trade. In 1620, war between this</b> <b>ruler and (+)</b> <b>Jahangir occurred over the city of Kandahar. The Shirley brothers helped</b> <b>reform the army of this shah, who reduced the power of the Qizilbash. In a 1603 war against the (*)</b> Ottoman Empire, this Persian ruler regained land lost by Tahmasp I in the Treaty of Amasya. This ruler moved his capital from Qazvin to Isfahan. For the points, name this great ruler of Safavid Persia.", "answer": "Shah<b> Abbas</b> I (or Shah<b> Abbas</b> the Great of Persia)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A man in this family was chosen to buy land for the Massachusetts State House and used that post to buy land from John Singleton Copley and develop it as Beacon Hill. Tax collector (+) John Robinson beat a man from this family in the head causing mental illness, and another member of this family used the pseudonym \u201cA Columbian Parrot\u201d and married James Warren. A Massachusetts politician from this family used the phrase, (*)</b> \u201ctaxation without representation.\u201d For the points, name this Boston Brahmin family whose patriot sympathizers included brother and sister James Jr. and Mercy.", "answer": "<b> Otis</b> family", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A resistance unit founded by these people was once known as King Peacock, in reference to the Peacock Angel. Three hundred of these people were said to have been killed on a single day in Tal Afar. The magazine (+)</b><em><b> Dabiq</b></em><b> contains articles justifying the enslavement</b> <b>of these people, who were targeted in Nineveh Province in the (*)</b> Sinjar Massacre. John Kerry claimed that the attacks in Northern Iraq against these people constituted genocide. ISIS has systematically targeted, for the points, what completely endogamous, Kurdish-speaking ethnic group of northern Iraq?", "answer": "<b> Yazidi</b>s (or<b> Yezidi</b>s; prompt on Kurds before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>A character who lives in this country is nicknamed \u201cMinke\u201d because of his resemblance to a monkey and first appeared in the novel</b><em><b> This Earth of Mankind</b></em><b>. The Cultivation System policy forced farmers in this country to grow sugar and coffee instead of rice, as detailed</b> <b>in (+)</b> <b>Multatuli\u2019s novel</b><em><b> Max Havelaar</b></em><b>. As part of the New Order, this country\u2019s author</b> <b>Multatuli\u2019s novel</b><em><b> Max Havelaar</b></em><b>. As part of the New Order, this country\u2019s author</b> <b>Pramoedya Ananta Toer was sent to a prison camp on (*)</b> <b>Pramoedya Ananta Toer was sent to a prison camp on (*)</b> Buru Island. For the points, name this former Dutch colony where many intellectuals were suppressed when Suharto came to power.", "answer": "<b> Indonesia</b>", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "<b>A message from leaders in this place was smuggled by Jan Karski to Szmul Zygelbojm [ZHEE-gul-boim], who promptly committed suicide. A bridge over Chlodna [HWOD-na] Street connected two sections of this place. This place was led by Adam Czerniakow,</b> <b>who also committed suicide. (+)</b> <b>Deportations from this place were carried out from the</b> <b>Umschlagplatz. A collection of photographs about an event led by Mordechai Anielewicz in this place is named after the (*)</b> SS officer who put down that event, Jurgen Stroop. For the points, name this place, where Jews were forced to live until an 1943 uprising in the Polish capital.", "answer": "<b> Warsaw Ghetto</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Richard Nixon \u201cpassed over 240 generals\u201d to confirm this man as Lieutenant General. This man, who was almost killed by a land mine planted by Red Army Faction member Rolf Clemens Wagner, had his namesake \u201cspeak\u201d described as \u201clanguage characterized by</b> <b>pompous obscurity.\u201d H.R. Haldeman was replaced by this man as (+)</b> <b>White House Chief</b> <b>of Staff following the Watergate Scandal. This man noted \u201cConstitutionally, gentlemen, you have the president, the vice president, and the (*)</b> secretary of state in that order\u201d while waiting for Vice President George H.W. Bush to arrive at the White House in 1981. For the points, name this man who proclaimed, \u201cI am in control here\u201d after the attempted assassination of Ronald Reagan.", "answer": "Alexander Meigs \u201cAl\u201d<b> Haig</b> Jr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Description acceptable. Glen McLaughlin collected a set of over 250 maps that depicted this misconception, which was at one point disproven by Eusebio Kino. The origin of this misconception is thought to be the book</b><em><b> Las sergas de Esplandi\u00b4an</b></em><b>, which describes this place as home to a race of black Amazonian women. Despite Mercator\u2019s creation of maps</b> <b>that (+)</b> <b>didn\u2019t fall prey to this myth, and despite Francisco de Ulloa\u2019s expedition that</b> <b>found that Tiburon and the Colorado River were part of the same landmass, proponents of this theory claimed that the supposed Strait of Anian connected to the Sea of (*) </b> Cortez. Well into the 18th century, some geographers subscribed to, for the points, what false theory that a Mexican peninsula was not connected to the mainland?", "answer": "the idea that (Baja)<b> California is an island</b> (accept answers relating to the<b> Island of </b>(Baja)<b> California</b>; accept descriptive answers related to the Spanish belief that Baja<b> California</b> was<b> not part of the mainland United States/North America</b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b>A ruler of this region named Svatopluk I sent John of Venice to meet Pope John VIII over the language used for liturgy. After Louis the German placed Rastislav in control of a\u201cgreat\u201d empire named for this region, invitations for \u201cteachers\u201d from Constantinople were sent out, leading Saints Cyril and Methodius to come and create the (+) Glagolitic Script. Ruling from an adjacent region with capital at Prague, the Premyslid Dynasty annexed this region under Boleslaus I. Capitals of this region included Olomouc and Brno, and this region was once merged with its part of its northern neighbor, (*) </b> Silesia. Forming part of a Nazi Protectorate, for the points, name this region of the Czech Republic that was often historically paired with Bohemia.", "answer": "<b> Moravia</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man published an influential study of Western orchestra in his 1844</b><em><b> Treatise on </b><b>Instrumentation</b></em><b>. This composer set the Vehmic trials of Medieval Germany to his unfinished</b> <b>opera</b><em><b> The Free Judges</b></em><b>, which he recycled into the second movement of his (+)</b> <em><b>Grand</b></em> <em><b>Funeral and Triumphal Symphony</b></em><b>. This man adapted Virgil\u2019s</b><em><b> Aeneid</b></em><b> into his opera</b><em><b> Les </b><b>Troyens</b></em><b>. He included a rendition of the Rakoczy March in his \u201cdramatic legend\u201d entitled (*) </b><em>The Damnation of Faust</em>. This composer of<em> Harold in Italy</em> included a \u201cMarch to the Scaffold\u201d in another work. For the points, name this French Romantic composer best known for<em> Symphonie Fantastique</em>.", "answer": "Hector<b> Berlioz</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "A Kentucky statute calling for this practice in the form of posters was found to be unconstitutional in the 1980 case</b><em><b> Stone v. Graham</b></em><b>, which applied the (*) </b> <em>Lemon</em> test. For the points, name this educational activity that, to be legal in public schools, must not violate the Establishment Clause of the First Amendment.", "answer": "<b> religious education</b> in public schools (accept descriptive equivalents; prompt on partial answers, like \u201cteaching\u201d or \u201creligious practice;\u201d do not accept or prompt on school prayer) (27) <b>Skunkha ruled over a subgroup of these people named for the fact that they wore</b> <b>pointed caps. In the fourth book of his</b><em><b> Histories</b></em><b>, Herodotus describes these people as having \u201clived in tent-covered wagons.\u201d A sculpture showing two of these people shooting</b> <b>arrows was found in present day (+)</b> <b>Kerch. In Krasnodai Krai, golden throne remains</b> <b>Kerch. In Krasnodai Krai, golden throne remains</b> <b>were found in a characteristic tomb of these people known as a (*)</b> <b>were found in a characteristic tomb of these people known as a (*)</b> <em>kurgan</em>. Persian sources often refer to these people as the Saka. For the points, name these nomads of Iranian descent who lived along the Eurasian steppe. ANSWER:<b> Scyth</b>ians", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This leader, who promoted the creation of khutors to empower agricultural peasants, ignored the Vyborg Manifesto on Finnish independence. This figure tried to implement the</b> <b>reforms of Sergei Witte but was opposed by the Kadets party. This man (+)</b> <b>dissolved</b> <b>the Second Duma for being too liberal and set up anti-rebellion courts that used nooses nicknamed his \u201cneckties.\u201d This man was (*)</b> assassinated while watching<em> The Tale of Tsar Saltan</em> in Kiev. For the points, name this Prime Minister under Nicholas II who attempted to make reforms after the Revolution of 1905.", "answer": "Pyotr<b> Stolypin</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}